<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: gadgets | Rust 'n Stuffs]]></title>
  <link href="http://cmr.github.io/blog/categories/gadgets/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://cmr.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-16T00:34:34-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://cmr.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Corey Richardson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Asus Vivobook X200]]></title>
    <link href="http://cmr.github.io/blog/2014/01/30/asus-vivobook-x200/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-30T01:36:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://cmr.github.io/blog/2014/01/30/asus-vivobook-x200</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently upgraded my aging <a href="http://amzn.to/1fhxWj4">Acer Aspire One</a> with a
new <a href="http://amzn.to/1e9k4ct">Asus Vivobook</a>. It was running a really slow
Intel Atom processor, one of the first generations. It literally took a day to
bootstrap Rust, and not all of that time was spent swapping! It worked well
for what I originally bought it for, which was as a dumb terminal SSHing into
my desktop. I wanted to upgrade to something that could actually run OpenGL
things, as well as browse the web without me wanting to give up and go to bed.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The vivobook has served these purposes very well, and at a price that I find
very compelling. It has a decent keyboard layout, as well as a fairly nice
screen, though the viewing angle leaves much to be desired. The webcam and
microphone are of good quality. It has full OpenGL 3.3 (possibly later
versions, once Mesa supports them). It can max out Xonotic and still be
relatively playable (15-20 FPS), with 40+ FPS at high quality. The CPU is only
dual-core, however. It also only has 2G of non-upgradable RAM, which is
problematic but was still an upgrade from the older netbook. The screen also
goes very dim (yay my eyes!), and fairly bright too.</p>

<p>I would recommend it to anyone looking for a cheap laptop. It fits my
ssh-heavy usecase perfectly. My only hesitation is the battery. It only lasts
about 2.5 hours, and almost as long to charge. I bought this after sending
back a <a href="http://amzn.to/1fhALRc">similarly-priced Chromebook</a>, due to the
Chromebook&rsquo;s unfortunate keyboard layout, and poor screen quality.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
