<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: personal | Rust 'n Stuffs]]></title>
  <link href="http://cmr.github.io/blog/categories/personal/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://cmr.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-30T01:59:01-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://cmr.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Corey Richardson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Intellectual Growth]]></title>
    <link href="http://cmr.github.io/blog/2014/01/30/intellectual-growth/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-30T00:15:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://cmr.github.io/blog/2014/01/30/intellectual-growth</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have a <a href="http://amzn.to/1aJdedm">textbook on logic</a>, I found it at the
<a href="http://cmr.github.io/blog/2014/01/06/reading-old-things/">dump</a> probably 3
years ago, during my second year of high school. I tried working through it
many times, but simply could not wrap my head around some of the concepts it
presents. In particular, I found its treatment of formal languages to be
very confusing. I could, for the most part, follow the material as I read it,
but attempting any of the exercises quickly became an exercise in futility.</p>

<p>Currently, I am in the so-called &ldquo;Foundations&rdquo; course (MA211) at my
<a href="http://clarkson.edu/">university</a>. Currently it is covering basic logic:
quantifiers, proofs, etc. Suddenly, I find myself able to tackle some of the
problems from the earlier textbook. Indeed, it is actually starting to make
sense. I find this feeling, the wave of understanding of a previously
impenetrable subject, very pleasant. It usually corresponds with a massive
increase in breadth of understanding, as I make connections to other subjects.
Hopefully I&rsquo;ll get these moments more often as I intensify my studies.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reading Old Things]]></title>
    <link href="http://cmr.github.io/blog/2014/01/06/reading-old-things/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-06T19:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://cmr.github.io/blog/2014/01/06/reading-old-things</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m learning Haskell. I&rsquo;m doing this for many reasons, but the most important
is to expand my knowledge and form a more principled understanding of
languages. So, I&rsquo;m reading a <a href="http://www.stanford.edu/class/cs242/readings/backus.pdf">paper</a>. It&rsquo;s a very good paper, but the
thing most striking about it is its age. 1977! My father was five. It occurred
to me that I read a lot of old things. I grab interesting books from book
sales, yard sales, thrift shops, and the &ldquo;Transfer Station &amp; Recycling Center&rdquo;
(aka the dump). Most of the time they&rsquo;re garbage, but I sometimes find true
gems. It&rsquo;s how I discovered Plato&rsquo;s <em>The Republic</em>, among other things. The
best part about reading older books is that they often strip away decades of
intellectual cruft that can accumulate around a subject, be it jargon or just
gross mutation of ideas.  Especially reading some foundational papers, or
books that were written when a subject was still young and exciting, a very
good historical perspective can be developed. I often find a conceptual
clarity that most new books simply don&rsquo;t give.</p>

<p>On the other hand, I&rsquo;ve yet to find old code that was truly worth reading. Old
code is frequently buggy, poorly written, or just plain unfinished. No code
remains dormant for too long. The only exception I can think of is TeX.</p>

<p>Observation bias? Perhaps. It could be that that&rsquo;s the only reason these books
have survived so long. Try reading some older books and papers. <a href="mailto:corey@octayn.net">Let me know
how it goes</a>. Have some suggestions for great books
and papers, old or others? I&rsquo;d like to hear those too.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ACM ICPC: What I Learned]]></title>
    <link href="http://cmr.github.io/blog/2013/10/20/acm-icpc-what-i-learned/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-20T10:47:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://cmr.github.io/blog/2013/10/20/acm-icpc-what-i-learned</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday I participated in my first <a href="http://icpc.baylor.edu/">programming
contest</a>. It was very fun, though challenging, and I
learned a fair bit during it. <!-- more --> The content consisted of teams of
3 working to solve 6 problems as fast as possible. The problems ranged from
trivial (repeated arithmetic) to moderately complex.</p>

<h2>Problem solving is fun.</h2>

<p>I already knew this, but it has been some time since I&rsquo;ve done intense
problem solving. It was nice to sit down for a few hours and bang my head
on a problem. Creative problem solving just <em>feels</em> good, in a way that most
activities don&rsquo;t.</p>

<h2>I don&rsquo;t know much about algorithms or data structures</h2>

<p>Of course I know the basic search and sorts, but anything involving
anything more complex than binary trees is beyond my current knowledge. A
few of the problems were solved very elegantly with tree operations. I was
unable to come up with a way to express the operation I wanted to perform.
It&rsquo;s a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Longest_path_problem">standard problem</a>
which I had not been aware of.</p>

<p>Now that I <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/There_are_known_knowns">know what I don&rsquo;t
know</a>, I can expand my
knowledge.</p>

<h2>C++&rsquo;s iostreams are quite nice</h2>

<p>Previously I haven&rsquo;t been a fan of iostreams, due to their misplaced
pedagogical use. But, for simply reading whitespace-separated data from stdin
and outputting the same to stdout, there probably isn&rsquo;t anything easier. I
might implement something similar (though not using the <code>&gt;&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;&lt;</code>
operators).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rust Hiatus]]></title>
    <link href="http://cmr.github.io/blog/2013/10/14/rust-hiatus/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-14T04:05:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://cmr.github.io/blog/2013/10/14/rust-hiatus</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m taking a temporary hiatus from all Rust work, to focus on academics. This
includes IRC and <a href="http://docs.octayn.net">http://docs.octayn.net</a>. I will continue to publish This
Week in Rust. If you need to contact me for any reason, please
<a href="send%20me%20an%20email">mailto:corey@octayn.net</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Reflection]]></title>
    <link href="http://cmr.github.io/blog/2013/06/15/a-reflection/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-15T08:21:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://cmr.github.io/blog/2013/06/15/a-reflection</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I graduated high school. It was quite a journey and I feel some
reflection is due.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h1>Regrets</h1>

<p>Randy Pausch said &ldquo;It is not the things we do in life that we regret on our
death bed. It is the things we do not.&rdquo; I agree with this. Fortunately, I have
few regrets about high school. I did not party, drink, or drug. I did not
participate in many clubs. I did not make many friends. I did, however, study,
almost constantly. Not for tests or anything academic, as my transcript shows
and my classmates can affirm, but my interests. I have learned more about my
passion, computers, than I ever thought existed when I first got started.</p>

<p>I have not been the most diligent student. Frequently I did not complete my
work. This was probably a bad decision, but I justified it with the (dubiously
attributed) Twain quote, &ldquo;Never let your schooling interfere with your
education,&rdquo; although it was initially laziness combined with depression. As
far back as 4th grade I&rsquo;ve been struggling to keep up with various assignments
(I recall being a few chapters behind in math homework. Mrs. Marrotte made me
stay after school every day until it was finished.) Later on, especially
7th-11th grade, it was hard to rile up motivation to do homework when I could
barely rile up motivation to continue being alive.</p>

<p>By the time I had gone through counseling and started an anti-depressant and
could function like a healthy human, I found I didn&rsquo;t have the skills to do
what needed to be done. I had not had practice or experience doing non-trivial
activities that I did not care about. I continue to struggle with this. It&rsquo;s
part procrastination too, which there&rsquo;s no excuse for. Another Randy Pausch
quote applies here: &ldquo;I&rsquo;ve always believed that if you took one tenth the
energy you put into complaining and applied it to solving the problem, you&rsquo;d
be surprised by how well things can work out.&rdquo;</p>

<p>But I don&rsquo;t regret not completing all of my work. Even if I did not finish and
pass in the homework, I did learn the content rather well. I wasn&rsquo;t content
not understanding something (except transcendentalism, but that is its own
story). I regret not making the most of my time in school. I could have been
much more engaged with the community of my peers. I&rsquo;m not sure that I actually
desire that difference, though. Time spent with my peers was instead spent
studying, programming, or playing video games. I graduate with 2 of my close
friends and a handful of good acquaintances (I use &ldquo;friend&rdquo; very reservedly).</p>

<p>I definitely regret not being more involved and dedicated to Destination
Imagination. It&rsquo;s a great program and I feel like I let down my teammates (and
probably frustrated the advisor). This also applies to science club and mock
trial, though to a lesser extent.</p>

<p>I really wish depression hadn&rsquo;t hit me like a train. It was manageable until
9th grade. From there it was a downward spiral of self-hatred, cutting, and
suicidal thoughts (and one attempt sophomore year). I know we are the sum of
our experience, and mine have made me stronger, but I would trade it in in a
heartbeat.</p>

<h1>Thanks</h1>

<p>Beyond teaching the standard curricula, I owe some teachers huge amounts of
thanks (roughly in chronological order):</p>

<ul>
<li>Mrs. Cook for encouraging me to be, as she phrased it, &ldquo;an odd duck.&rdquo; I was
very sad to see her leave after a single year at the school, she was a
good teacher.</li>
<li>Julia Zimmerman and Paul Kreiner (during Junction 2011 at MIT) for so many
reasons. They were constantly encouraging, even when my writing was
terrible. They taught me how appreciate science fiction and all forms of
writing, showing the science behind writing through linguistics.</li>
<li>Mrs. Stroshine for <em>really</em> teaching how to analyze and appreciate usage of
the English language, and also for putting up with me as I finished Junior
English my Senior Year. I procrastinated so much and was actually afraid of
you (although that construction was entirely in my head, you are a very nice
person). You are a fantastic teacher and I hope you enjoy your retirement.</li>
<li>Mr. Smith for his passion for history. It has definitely rubbed off on me,
especially your message that history isn&rsquo;t static, it is constantly open to
reinterpretation as more evidence is presented.</li>
<li>Mr. Fazio for his gentle encouragement and toleration of my (usually
advanced, sometimes off-topic) questions in the middle of his lessons, as
well as not giving up near the end of the year in Senior Math Topics. I did
actually learn in that class.</li>
<li>Dr. Kaplan for fostering a healthy skepticism in me. Your occasional
off-track discussions that you allowed (although never skipping a beat with
the curriculum) throughout our two years were always informative. These will
stick with me longer than how to balance redox reactions.</li>
<li>Ms. Gigliello for understanding me almost uncannily (supposedly her daughter
is just like me. Which is, of course, a good thing). The discussions you
(lightly moderated) during class never failed to engage me. Circle time is a
wonderful invention.</li>
<li>Mr. Dunn for letting me work in his room all the time and for his farewell
address. You are a great asset to the school, and your retirement has
definitely been earned.</li>
</ul>


<p>And finally</p>

<ul>
<li>Mr. Kuhn. You are possibly the best teacher I ever had, especially
considering some of the most important lessons you taught me were outside of
any class I was in. You always challenged me to think creatively and to
stretch beyond myself, but within my means. My biggest regret is not
spending more time with you this year (I felt awful for the DI fiasco, I was
embarrassed to even see you in the hall: an unfounded feeling I know).</li>
</ul>


<p>Not only have you taught me your respective curricula, you have <em>changed the
way I think</em>. Your influence, and my appreciation, can not be overstated. You
do not get paid nearly enough for what you do.</p>

<p>There are some non-teachers that get some love too:</p>

<ul>
<li>Joanne Walsh, who always gave me crap for being late to school. You are an
amazing, patient, kind person. It meant a lot to me to see you at
graduation. Thank you.</li>
<li>Roni Hoffmanm. You were my mom away from home and always made sure I was
behaving as a decent human should. During conversation you called yourself a
&ldquo;peon&rdquo; and a &ldquo;little person.&rdquo; Nothing could be further than the truth. You
are incredibly important and a great role model.</li>
</ul>


<p>I will not miss Monadnock, but I will miss the faculty. The quality of the
teachers is very high. The political changes happening around them are
unfortunate.</p>

<h1>The future</h1>

<p>I will be studying Computer Science at Clarkson University in the fall. I will
not squander my time there like I did my time in high school.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
